Today's דף *daf* is י"ט *Yud Tes* 19. We pick up in
the middle of
י"ח עמוד ב' *Yud Ches Amud Beis* and we are dealing with
אמה amah. עבריה *Ama Ivriya* and עבד עברי eved ivri, *Eved Ivri*
and comparisons and differences. And now we are also focusing in on
this issue of ייעוד yiyud *yi'ud* that אם לבנו ייעדנה *im livno
yiyadena*, אשר לא יעדה *asher lo ye'ada*, that with כסף kesef *kessef*
the girl, young girl, she's under 12, who's bought as a slave,
seems like the primary goal was that in order that she should
get married to the guy,
and that's called ייעוד yiyud *yi'ud*. He chooses to make her into
his wife, or he can do it for his son. So now
we're going to have the rest from here for the rest of
today, finishing yesterday's דף *daf* and today's דף *daf* are really focused
on this issue of ייעוד yiyud *yi'ud*. So let's take a look.
We start about six lines from the top on י"ח עמוד ב'
*Yud Ches Amud Beis*. בעי רבא בר אבוה *Ba'ei Rava bar Avuh*,
Rava bar Avuh asked, ייעוד yiyud נישואין nisuin, עושה oseh, או אירוסין
erusin. עושה *yi'ud nisuin osa o erusin osa*? Right? We've had similar
questions if by קידושי ביאה biah *kiddushei biah* we wanted to know,
since that creates that immediate intimacy and physical connection, קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*
usually is a stage before she's living together, they're living together in
the same home. So we had that question whether קידושי ביאה bi'ah
*kiddushei biah* goes all the way straight to נישואין nisuin, *nisuin*. Here
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is asking a similar question. She's living in
his house as a slave, but she's living in his house. Now
he does ייעוד yiyud, *yi'ud*. Is that really a stage prior to
the נישואין nisuin, *nisuin* or does that automatically create the reality that
they're living in the same home and that's נישואין nisuin, *nisuin*? Okay,
so does the ייעוד yiyud. *yi'ud* create אירוסין erusin. *erusin* or create
נישואין nisuin *nisuin*?
Yes, I already have a question. Just on the fund, if the
ייעוד yiyud *yi'ud* really is the goal is the potential marriage, right,
right.
So does the אב *av* have to be in debt to the
person or can he just, in other words, indenture his daughter because
he wants that marriage?
Yeah, I mean theoretically, well first of all, it's not at all,
even if the father is selling his daughter primarily because he needs
the money, it's not clear that he owes money to this person.
He might owe to creditors and he's selling her to someone else
so that he can pay off his creditors, number one. But would
a father do it if he had no financial obligations just because
he thought it was a path towards קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin*? Maybe, it's
hard to imagine though because even though the תורה Torah *Torah* goes
out of its way, the point of the תורה Torah *Torah* is
to emphasize that this girl deserves the same degree of respect and
dignity and protection and rights, nevertheless one has to imagine that that
is not, you know, one would much more get married the normal
way than through the route of slavery. So anyway, all right. בעי
רבא בר אבוה ייעוד yiyud, נישואין nisuin, עושה או אירוסין eirusin? עושה
*Ba'ei Rava bar Avuh yi'ud nisuin osa o erusin osa*. נפקא מינה
*Nafka mina*, what would be the נפקא מינה *nafka mina*? ליורשה ולטמא
לה ולהפר נדריה *Le'yorsha u'letamei lah u'lehafer nedareha*, all the נפקא מינה
*nafka minas* of being a נשואה *nisuah*. If she dies, does he
inherit her? If she dies and he's a כהן kohen, *kohen*, is
he מטמא *metamei* to her? Can he annul her vows? Could also
have asked about his obligations to her to provide, you know, support,
etc. שארה כסותה ועונתה *She'era kesuta ve'onata*, all the realities of נישואין
nissuin? *nisuin*. Does that kick in right away or is there needed
a separate stage? Okay. נפקא מינה למאי *Nafka mina le'mai*? What do
you say? תא שמע ta shema: *Ta shema*. בבגדו בה bevigdo vah
*Be'vigdo bah*, what we discussed yesterday, that he cannot sell her after
there cannot be like שפחה אחר שפחה shifcha achar shifcha *shifcha achar
shifcha* or שפחה אחר אישות shifcha achar ishus. *shifcha achar ishous* depending
on how you read the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. So one way we
read the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is כיון שפירש טליתו עליה שוב אינו
רשאי למוכרה *kivan she'piras taliso aleha shuv eino rashai lemochra*. בבגדו *Be'vigdo*
reading the word as בגד *beged*, once he spread his garment over
her, he cannot sell her. So the father cannot sell his daughter
after a שפחה shifcha. *shifcha* which became a ייעוד yiyud. *yi'ud*, okay,
so that's שפחה אחר אישות shifcha achar ishut. *shifcha achar ishous*. But
the אישות ishus? *ishous* came through this act of ייעוד yiyud *yi'ud*.
Now how is that relevant? So it says ובאיבוני הוא דלא מזבין
לה *u've'ivunei hu de'lo mazbin lah*. So what he can't do is
he can't sell her after this ייעוד yiyud, *yi'ud* if then the
master dies. הא ייעודי מייעד mi'ayid. לה *Ha yi'udei me'ya'id lah*, he
could be מייעד mi'ayid *meya'id* her again, which really means he could
be מקדש mekadesh *mekadesh* her again. Okay, ואי אמרת נישואין עושה ve'i
amrat nissuin osah, *ve'i amart nisuin osa*, but one minute, if the
ייעוד yiyud *yi'ud* created נישואין nissuin *nisuin*, כיון דנישאת שוב אין לאביה
רשות reshus בה *kivan de'nisat shuv ein le'avi reshus bah*. So once
there's נישואין nissuin *nisuin* the father has no longer any rights over
her, right? So what we discussed yesterday was here's this girl, okay,
she gets sold to the guy, okay, here's the father, okay, here's
dad, okay, anyway, so she gets sold to him, okay, and then
that becomes ייעוד yiud. *yi'ud*, okay, which okay, so now that's אישות
ishus? *ishous*, now she's his married, okay, then he dies, okay, and
then it says the father can't sell her again, right? לעם נכרי
לא ימשול למכרה בבגדו בה bevigdo vah *Lamnochri lo
yimshol lemochra be'vigdo bah*.
So which means, right, so now he dies, he can't sell her
again, so that means there's no אין שפחה אחר אישות ein shifcha
achar ishus. *ein shifcha achar ishous*, right? That's what we did yesterday,
right? Everybody with me here? Yep. Okay. So the point is fine,
but that suggests I'll tell you... So it's a little different than
the גמרא, Gemara that suggests there's a specific איסור issur for him
to now sell her again as a slave. But fundamentally, she's still
under his control after the master dies; she fundamentally still under the
control of the father. So for example, the father might be able
to now be מקדש mekadesh her, okay? Because basically it's clear she's
under his control, the תורה Torah is just telling us he's not
allowed to sell her again as a slave. All right, but the
point is how is he now back under the father's control if
this ייעוד yiud created נישואין, nissuin. then once a girl has had
נישואין, nissuin, she's totally out of the father's control.
He had ייעוד yiud on her by the way in the second...
Oh well, she's got... that's a good point. Okay. Anyway, so it
says, okay, ואי אמרת נישואין עושה כיון דניסת שוב אין לאביה רשות
בה. ve'i amart nisuin osa kivan deniset shuv ein le'aviha reshut bah.
So why do you need a פסוק pasuk to prevent him from
doing something after ייעוד yiud if she's already in נישואין, nissuin, she's
out of the father's control? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא לאו
שמע מינה אירוסין עושה, ela lav shema mina erusin osa, you see
that it makes only אירוסין. eirusin, Pretty good proof. אמר רב נחמן
בר יצחק הכא בקידושין דעלמא קיימינן. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hacha
bekiddushin de'alma kayminan. No, no, no, no, we're not talking about בבגדו
בה bevigdo vah that he became her husband through ייעוד yiud after
שפחות. shifchus. We're talking about a completely different scenario; this is a
very weak read of the ברייתא. braisa. והכי קאמר: vehachi ka'amar: כיון
שמסרה אביה למי שנתחייב בשאירה כסותה ועונתה, kivan shemasra aviha lemi shenitchayev
beshera kesusa ve'onasa, if the father had already done קידושין kiddushin with
her, and בבגדו בה be'vigdo bah not about the context of ייעוד,
yiud? but בבגדו בה be'vigdo bah general context of somebody who became
her husband, if the father had already married her off and it
was just קידושין kiddushin, and then the husband died, שוב אינו יכול
למוכרה, shuv eino yachol lemachra, then he can't sell her. Okay, so
what we're saying is this idea that it's saying after this guy
dies after קידושין kiddushin he can no longer sell her, אין שפחות
אחר אישות, ein shifchus achar ishut, is not talking about the case
in the פרשה parsha about that he had initially sold her as
a שפחה. shifcha? It's talking about there was קידושין, kiddushin, okay? לאמה
היא לא ימשול למכרה בבגדו בה, le'ama hi lo yimshol lemachra bevigdo
vah, it's telling you after קידושין kiddushin. to another man and then
he dies, and now she was just going back to the father
because it was only קידושין, kiddushin he can't sell her as a
slave. The father can sell his daughter as a slave if she
was never married before, but if he had once married her earlier,
he can't sell her as a slave, if she was never מקודשת.
mekudeshet. But the תורה Torah is not talking about a scenario where
there had been ייעוד. yi'ud Okay, obviously a very hard read in
the ברייתא. braisa. Anyway, now we go... so that's... but... so that
was ostensibly, not ostensibly, it really was a good proof that ייעוד
yi'ud. did not create נישואין, nissuin but we said we're not talking
about ייעוד, yi'ud we're talking about קידושין. kiddushin Okay, תא שמע: ta
shema אין מוכר לקרובים, ein mocher likrovim,
you cannot sell her to relatives because then there's no possibility of
ייעוד. yi'ud משום רבי אלעזר אמרו מוכר לקרובים. mishum Rabbi Elazar amru
mocher likrovim. Rabbi Eliezer says you can sell her to relatives. Your
brother, right, your father, your son. Okay, ושוין שמוכר אלמנה לכהן גדול
גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט. veshavin shemocher almana lekohen gadol grusha vachalutza lekohen
hedyot.
But even though there's a question can you sell her to a
relative where קידושין kiddushin would not be תופס, tofes, if he would
try to do ייעוד yi'ud it wouldn't even take effect, everybody agrees
you can sell her to a man that there's an איסור issur
for him to marry her or him to marry her, but that
קידושין kiddushin would still take effect if it was done. What's a
case where there's an איסור issur to marry but קידושין kiddushin would
still take effect? When it's not a relative, but it's an איסור
לאו issur lav like a כהן, kohen a כהן גדול kohen gadol
to an אלמנה, almana, a כהן kohen. to a גרושה grusha etc.
That he can do, and even though it would be אסור assur
to do the ייעוד, yi'ud the ייעוד yi'ud is still theoretically possible
because if done it would take effect.
Okay, why is there a תא שמע Ta shema, here? You're still
trying to prove the original point?
Yep, they're trying to prove whether it's נישואין nissuin. or אירוסין.
eirusin They're still working on it.
Yep. Okay. האי אלמנה היכי דמי? hai almana hechi dami? Now
what's the case that the father is selling his daughter who's an
אלמנה almana as a slave? Okay, how did she become an אלמנה?
almana? אילימא דקידשה נפשה, ilima dekidsha nafsha, if she became an אלמנה
almana through this underage girl marrying herself and then her husband died,
אלמנה קרי לה, almana kari lah, how could you call her an
אלמנה? almana? The קידושין kiddushin. wasn't even binding.
An underage girl can't marry herself. אלא דקידשה אביה, ela dekidsha aviha,
it must be that her father married her off to some guy
and the guy died and now she's an אלמנה. almana. And the
question is can he marry her off again to a כהן גדול?
kohen gadol? So מי מצי מזבין לה? mi matzi mazbin lah? One
minute! But if the father had initially married her off to some
guy and the guy died and she's an אלמנה, almana, how can
we now be discussing him selling her as a שפחה? shifcha. והא
אין אדם מוכר את בתו לשפחה אחר אישות. veha ein adam mocher
es bito leshifcha achar ishut.
That would be a case of שפחות אחר אישות, shifchus achar ishut,
which we're assuming like the תנא tanna who says that that's not
legitimate.
Okay, so we
have this father marrying his daughter who's either an אלמנה almana or
a גרושה grusha to a כהן גדול kohen gadol or כהן. kohen
So how does she become an אלמנה almana or גרושה? grusha? Must
be he had married her once and now the guy... so fine,
but then the guy died or divorced her. But one
minute! If the father had already married her once, he can't sell
her now as a slave. אין שפחות אחר אישות, ein shifchus achar
ishut, whether it's קידושין kiddushin or נישואין, nissuin אין שפחות אחר אישות.
ein shifchus achar ishut. So what's the scenario that he could be
selling her now? as a slave and she's an אלמנה almanah or
a גרושה gerushah because אין שפחה אחר אישות. ein shifcha achar ishus.
So what's the case? Okay. ואמר רב נחמן בר יצחק הכא בהקדשה
ייעוד Ve'amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak hacha behikdishah yiud דאתיא כרבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה de'asya k'Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda דאמר מעות הראשונות לאו לקידושין
ניתנו. de'amar ma'os harishonos lav le'kiddushin nitnu. Here
is how it works. Here's the scenario where he could be selling
her and she's an אלמנה. almanah. The first
she became an אלמנה almanah through an initial sale as a שפחה.
shifcha. Okay. So she was sold here as a שפחה. shifcha. It
started off as a שפחה. shifcha.
It started off as a שפחה. shifcha,
Okay.
And then this guy did ייעוד. yi'ud Now
did the father, was the father in this scenario מקדש mekadesh her
or not? Because the הלכה halacha is the father can't sell her
a second time as a slave if he sold her once as
קידושין. kiddushin, אין שפחה אחר אישות. ein shifcha achar ishus. So in
this case, did the father, did the father create the אישות? ishus?
So the question
here is, is the ייעוד yi'ud that the guy does, is that
something that's happening now later once the father's out of the picture
and then the father never sold her for אישות? ishus. The father
okay, or are we saying that the ייעוד yi'ud that's done hearkens
back to that original sale and that money of that original sale
now becomes כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin and therefore the father did sell
her for as
אישות? ishus So what we're saying is if we say מעות הראשונות
לאו לקידושין ניתנו, ma'os harishonos lav le'kiddushin nitnu, okay, and therefore the
father did not sell her for did not sell her as אישות.
ishus The father sold her as שפחה, shifcha then the אישות ishut.
came later and then this guy dies and then she becomes an
and now she's an אלמנה, almanah, okay. So now the father can
sell her as a slave because the father would be selling her
I mean it would be שפחה אחר שפחה shifcha achar shifcha, because
the father originally sold her as a שפחה shifcha. but it wouldn't
be שפחה אחר אישות. shifcha achar ishut The father had never been
מקדש mekadesh her. The guy was מקדש mekadesh her, the father was
never מקדש mekadesh her, so the father can now sell her as
a slave and we could discuss selling his daughter who's an אלמנה
almanah or גרושה gerushah to a כהן kohen or כהן גדול. kohen
gadol.
According to that only applies if he does it again if well
or if he did it the first time. Right, if he did
it the first time he in this case if this ייעוד yi'ud
is a new thing he never sold her for אישות in the
first time. Okay, that was something that happened separately, yes.
Can a כהן kohen, marry a girl whatever that was אלמנה מן
האירוסין?
almanah
min ha'eirusin? No. כהן גדול? kohen gadol? Yes. Okay, so why don't
we distinguish in this case at all between קידושין kiddushin versus נישואין?
nissuin Like why I mean I see the גמרא Gemara does it
but I would think this a lot about אלמנה.
almanah. This no because it's different.
במכר אדם בתו be'machar adam bito you know
there's no basis for it. I mean whatever oh you're saying because
the איסור issur of בבגדו בה is
well that's an interesting question if בבגדו בה suggests נישואין nissuin, maybe
understand the איסור issur ought to be only after נישואין nissuin but
then that gets to the that can't be because then the גמרא
Gemara then you wouldn't need a פסוק pasuk because then she would
already be out of his רשות if there was already נישואין.
nissuin I'm understanding why when the father sells her he's expecting that
or hoping that she's going to be married to the guy? What?
So that's the way I understand it, yeah. But that doesn't mean
that might have been the goal but that doesn't mean that that
was what the act was. The act was not a קידושין, kiddushin
the act the father did was selling her as a שפחה.
shifcha But it never happened when he first sells her even with
that goal it's never going to happen at the beginning of the
sale, right?
Correct, correct. But but if the money of the sale becomes transformed
into כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin it's still through an act that he
did. It's still he was part of that act of קידושין kiddushin.
as opposed to now we're saying that no, no, the whole act
occurred later. Was he a party to that act? Okay, in one
case he set up the groundwork but ultimately the guy did the
act with the with the girl as opposed to the other case
right it might you know that he he took the money and
later that money becomes money of קידושין kiddushin so he did the
act of קידושין.
kiddushin But I don't understand when do you separate the one from
the other? He sells his daughter, right?
He sells his daughter
with the goal that she's going to be married to the guy.
Right. So then if the guy does ייעוד yiud right he then
that money becomes כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin right?
According to one opinion but now we're working with the opinion that
the money doesn't become כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. That's that's exactly the
issue. If the money became כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin then the father
was מקדש mekadesh her and אין שפחה אחר אישות. ein shifcha achar
ishut If the money wasn't כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin and the כסף
קידושין kesef kiddushin was a new act that happened later okay not
based on the money that changed hands then the father wasn't מקדש
mekadesh her then it just happened that's exactly the question. What is
the act of קידושין kiddushin with ייעוד? yiud, Is it the money
that changed hands three years ago or is it some new act
that's happening now?
Even though it's the same money we're talking about. In other words
is there an additional money three years no?
But it might just be well I'm trying to we haven't gotten
to it yet but basically what we would say if it happened
later and not the original money is it's the fact that she
still owes him service and he's giving her back the service that's
still owed and that becomes the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, yeah. No.
No.
Okay, yeah, very good question. So he can the ייעוד yiud can
happen at any point along the six years. It could happen at
the end.
No, any point.
Okay, so she doesn't have to stay for... unlike the עבד עברי,
right, what we were saying is like on
a better contract, where she
is not bound...
well exactly. Right, well he wants to do the ייעוד. yiyud. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. אמר רב אמר
רב יצחק Amar Rav amar Rav Yitzchak כוחה בקידושי ייעוד kocha be'kiddushei
yi'ud ואליבא דרבי יהודה ve'aliba de'Rabbi Yehuda דאמר מעות ראשונות לאו לקידושין
ניתנו. de'amar ma'ot rishonot lav le'kiddushin nitnu. So the reason, only way
that he could be selling his daughter who's an אלמנה almanah or
a גרושה, gerushah, because he's not allowed to do it if he
had already married her. The only way he could do it is
if he had originally not married her off but sold her off.
Okay, presumably there's not a problem of שפחה אחר שפחה, shifcha achar
shifcha. he had only sold her off and the money he received
did not become כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, the קידושין Kiddushin thing happened
later not based on the money he received. Okay, and that's how
it's possible to discuss him marrying off his daughter who's an אלמנה
almanah or a גרושה. gerushah. Now, all of that was to get
to the fact that there had been ייעוד yiyud, and he was
still discussing his ability to marry off his daughter. ואי אמרת נישואין
nissuin עושה, and if ייעוד yiyud creates נישואין, nissuin. how could we
be discussing his ability to sell his daughter? She's already out of
his control. כיוון שנישאת שוב אין לאביה רשות בה. keivan she'niset shuv
ein le'aviha reshut bah. So that seems to be a pretty good
proof that even after ייעוד yiyud she's still only an ארוסה. arusah.
So the גמרא Gemara says ואלא מאי אירוסין עושה? ve'ela mai eirusin
osah? You want to say it does אירוסין? eirusin. So one minute.
ושווין שמוכרה, veshavin shemochrah,
it says that they agree that she that he can sell her
to a you know as a גרושה gerushah or אלמנה almanah to
a כהן, kohen okay. והאין אדם מוכר את בתו לשפחה אחר אישות.
ve'ein adam mocher et bito leshifcha achar ishut. So we still have
a problem. Okay, now this I've already told you the answer to
this. והשתא vehashta I don't even understand. Even if you said that
you did ייעוד yiyud? and it only created אירוסין, eirusin how can
he go ahead and sell her to now a כהן or a
כהן גדול? kohen gadol? That's still שפחה אחר אישות. shifcha achar ishut.
She had been married. Okay, but we already know the answer. The
גמרא's Gemara already said the answer is that she had been married
but he wasn't the one that married her off. Okay. אלא מאי
אית לך למימר ela mai it lach lemeimar שאני אירוסין דידה מאירוסין
דאביה. shani eirusin didah me'eirusin de'aviha. So clearly there's a difference. Did
she marry herself or did her father marry her? If her father
married her off then he's not allowed to sell her again. But
if she if she married herself, meaning the marriage happened later with
the ייעוד yiyud and he wasn't involved, then he would be able
to sell her again. Fine. So you can so once we establish
that, I'll tell you אפילו תימא נישואין עושה, afilu teima nissuin osah,
even if the ייעוד yiyud creates נישואין, nissuin שאני נישואין דידה מנישואין
דאביה. shani nissuin didah minissuin de'aviha. It's different if she created the
נישואין or her father created the נישואין. Now that's a very strange
idea because the issue by having rights after נישואין isn't like, oh
you did this one act to her, you're not allowed to do
another act to her. That's the idea of אין שפחה אחר אישות
ein shifcha achar ishut, and so on. Here the idea is just
the reality of having lived in another, being part of another man's
household takes her out of her father's household. So whether her father
did the נישואין or she did the נישואין, the reality is that
she left the father's household so he would not have any rights.
And that's what the גמרא Gemara says back. האי מאי? hai mai?
What type of comparison is that? בשלמא אירוסין מאירוסין שאני—look, bishlama eirusin
me'eirusin shani this has got to be the tersest גמרא Gemara ever
about because the whole it doesn't even you know explain anything, it
just sort of repeats the
words—בשלמא אירוסין מאירוסין שאני. bishlama eirusin me'eirusin shani. Look, I can make
a distinction between אירוסין eirusin and אירוסין. eirusin, The אירוסין eirusin by
the father, he's not allowed to resell her, but an אירוסין erusin
done by her, he is allowed to resell her. That makes the
difference, who did it, she or the father. אלא נישואין מנישואין מי
שאני? ela nissuin minissuin mi shani? But how can you say there's
a difference between one type of a נישואין and another type? Of
course the whole explanation is missing, but the point is what I
said. Okay, the reason the father loses control after נישואין is not
because he did the act of נישואין you know prevents him you
know from doing a different another type or an act afterwards. It's
the reality of having been in part of another man's household. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara pretty conclusively has proven, it never says explicitly
okay you're right it's a good proof, but it's pretty conclusively proved
that since we have these discussions of שפחה אחר אישות shifcha achar
ishut and all these types of things which means a scenario where
after ייעוד yiyud. she still could be under the father's control if
the master dies or divorces her or whatever shows that even after
ייעוד yi'ud it's only אירוסין, it's not yet נישואין. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara has pretty conclusively proved that, the fact that we have
to discuss that there was a קידושי ייעוד kiddushei yi'ud and then
the guy dies and now can the father resell her do another
case of קידושין kiddushin another case of שפחה shifcha shows that even
after ייעוד yi'ud she remains in an אירוסין state and not in
a נישואין state. Okay.
אירוסין דידה eirusin didah here doesn't mean she sells herself, it
means—yes it does, it means that if you say—how can—well, okay, we're
going to discuss that later, okay, but about how can she do
that, we're going to get up to that, but it still means
that fundamentally it wasn't the transaction with the father, it's between the
two of them. Now your question is where how can she do
it, she's a קטנה, ketanah, we'll get to that. Okay. So... Now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. לרב נחמן בר יצחק Le-Rav
Nachman bar Yitzchak אמר amar אפילו afillu רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi
Yose Beribi Yehuda מוסר mosar לשונות leshonot של shel קידושין kiddushin, נתנו.
nitnu. But wait a minute. We have a position that says we're
going to back get to it in a hopefully in a little
bit that everybody agrees, even רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose Beribi
Yehuda, we quoted before רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose Beribi Yehuda
said that it was not the כסף kessef of the sale that
became the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. It was the late later like
as I was sort of mentioned, it was the undone unfinished labor,
the remainder of the contract that became the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin.
Okay, that's how we sort of explained this scenario, that the father
never sold her off and therefore we can talk about him marrying
about her selling her again. But there's an opinion that says that
even לרב נחמן בר יצחק, Le-Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, even for רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose Beribi Yehuda, everybody agrees that it's the
original money that became כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. So if that's true,
במאי מוקימנא? be-mai mukimna? How do we have a discussion of a
father marrying his daughter who's an אלמנה almana or a גרושה? gerusha?
Because that means that the father must have married her. He must
have either done a קידושין kiddushin. or he must have done שפחות
shifchut and then that money became כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin because according
to some opinions, everybody agrees that the money is כסף קידושין, kesef
kiddushin, okay, the original money. So either way, the father originally married
her. So if the father originally married her, how can we be
discussing him now selling her as an אלמנה almana or as a
גרושה, gerusha, אין שפחה אחר אישות, ein shifcha achar ishut. and he
did the original אישות. So what can it be talking about? So
the גמרא Gemara says no, מוקימנא כרבי אליעזר mukimna ke-Rabbi Eliezer דאמר
de-amar לשפחה אחר שפחה הוא דלא מצי מזבין לה le-shifcha achar shifcha
hu dela matzi mazbin lah אבל לשפחה אחר אישות מצי מזבין לה.
aval le-shifcha achar ishut matzi mazbin lah. If you remember yesterday, there
were different opinions. We've been consistently assuming like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
that אין שפחה אחר אישות. shifcha achar ishut Maybe we think that
there's even that there is שפחה אחר שפחה. shifcha achar shifcha The
only thing you can't do is שפחה אחר אישות. shifcha achar ishut
But the גמרא Gemara says no, there's the opposite position of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that שפחה shifcha, אחר אישות is no problem, שפחה
אחר שפחה is a problem, but שפחה אחר אישות is not a
problem. And that's of course that's so funny, it was such an
easy answer, right? The גמרא Gemara. was sort of agonizing over how
do you just, how do you have a case of him marrying
of her selling her after she's an אלמנה almana or a גרושה?
gerusha? The answer could be, well, there's רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says שפחה אחר אישות is not a problem. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Anyway, the רמב״ם Rambam
פוסק posek that ייעוד yi'ud is אירוסין עושה, which certainly is where
the dominant proofs were in that גמרא. Gemara Now we have another
question. בעא
ריש לקיש: Ba'ei Reish Lakish: מהו שיעייד אדם לבנו קטן? Mahu she-ye-ayeid
adam l'veno katan? Now, the father, the guy who bought this daughter,
this girl, he can say I'm going to make you my wife,
that's ייעוד, yi'ud or he can say, you know what? I'm going
to make you my son's wife. Now here becomes an interesting question,
right? אם לבנו יעדנה, Im l'veno yedana, he is the one that
does the ייעוד yi'ud for the son. So what is the role
that the son has in this process and how much does the
son have to agree? How much does the son have to be
an adult? Can the son be a קטן? katan? Well yeah, can
the son be a קטן, katan, right? Which is interesting because normally
while we have the קטנה ketana as a minor who can be
in a קידושין דאורייתא, kiddushin d'Oraita,
we never seem to have a boy who could be in a
status of קידושין דאורייתא. kiddushin d'Oraita. Because normally, if you're the man,
you have to do the act of קידושין, kiddushin. and therefore you
have to be an adult to do the act of קידושין. kiddushin,
No, because there's no שליחות לקטן. shlichut le-katan. Okay, in general.
I'm saying you can never have a minor man boy in a
קידושין. kiddushin A girl can be in קידושין, kiddushin. a minor girl,
because the father can marry her off. But a minor boy cannot
because he's the agent, he can't do it himself, his act of
קידושין kiddushin is not good as a minor, he can't have an
adult do it, there's no שליחות לקטן. shlichut le-katan. So normally you
never have קידושי קטן, kiddushei katan, okay, a minor boy being in
קידושין. kiddushin But here the תורה Torah says the father can be
מיעד me-ayeid this girl for his son. Can he do it even
if his son
is
a
קטן?
katan? Okay. בנו אמר רחמנא בנו כל דהו. Beno amar Rachmana beno
kol d'hu. It says you can marry her off to your son,
any son, even if it's a
קטן. katan. Okay. או דילמא בנו דומיא דידיה: O dilma beno dumya
dideyh: מה הוא גדול אף בנו גדול. mah hu gadol af beno
gadol. The son has to be an adult, meaning maybe the father
is acting as like an appointed שליח shaliach or something, but we're
not changing the whole concept that for the man to enter into
marriage, the man has to be an adult. He fundamentally is the
one entering in, so even if the father is doing it for
him, it's only when he still is an adult. Okay. So אמר
רבי זירא תא שמע: Amar Rabbi Zeira ta shema: Come and hear.
Now again, we're not asking in general, a father cannot contract marriage
for his son. Even if his son is an adult, he can't
unless he's been made a שליח, shaliach, and certainly for a son
who's a קטן. katan. But here maybe the תורה Torah allows it.
Okay, so what's the הלכה? halacha? So אמר רבי זירא תא שמע,
Amar Rabbi Zeira ta shema, come here: איש. Ish. This is talking...
about the act of adultery. איש אשר ינאף את אשת רעהו. Ish
asher yinaf et eshet re'ehu. If a man commits adultery with his
with another man's wife, okay, or his neighbor's wife. איש, Ish, פרט
לקטן. prat lekatan. If a minor commits an act of adultery, then
he's not stoned, right? He's a minor, he's not liable for punishment.
The reason you needed the פסוק pasuk to tell you that is
because if the minor is over nine years old, the הלכה halacha
is that the הלכה halacha recognizes his act as an act of
sex, not that he should be punished, he's still under the age
of liability, but the woman who had sex with a minor, let's
say she's a married woman that has sex with a minor who's
over nine years old, that's an act of adultery and she's put
to death. Okay, so you have to tell us that even if
she would be put to death, he is not. אשר ינאף את
אשת רעהו, Asher yinaf et eshet re'ehu, that commits adultery with אשת
איש, eshet ish, excuse me, a man's wife, okay, that so פרט
לאשת קטן. prat leeshet katan. If a man committed adultery with the
wife of a minor, that's not... he's not put to death, that's
not adultery. So wait a minute, we got an interesting question. Who
ever heard of the wife of a minor? Why does the תורה
Torah have to exclude that from the punishment of adultery? Where do
you ever have that scenario of the wife of a minor? So
the גמרא Gemara says ואימא מיעד... ve'im tomar miyad... so first it
assumes, well,
let's say you could have a wife of a minor through ייעוד.
yi'ud. But אם כן מצינו אישה לקטן, im ken matzinu isha lekatan,
then why does the תורה Torah saying that you don't... it's not
adultery? If the תורה's Torah allowing for a form of קידושין Kiddushin
with a minor through ייעוד, yi'ud then
why is a person not liable for having committed adultery in that
case? So the גמרא Gemara turns it around. אלא מאי, Ela mai,
what do you want to say? אינו מיעד, Eino miyad, that you
cannot create ייעוד yi'ud. with a minor, so and there's never marriage
with a minor? So if there's never the reality of marriage with
a minor, why do you need the תורה Torah to exclude it
from punishment?
Okay, אמאי קא מייתר קרא, amai kammaidareikra, all right, well, that's the
question. תיפשוט מינה דמיעד. Tipshot minnad demiyad. So now we have two
ways of understanding, what does it mean when the תורה says you're
not liable for adultery with the wife of a minor? Is it
teaching you the הלכה halacha that there is no marriage with a
minor, that there was never a marriage all together, and it's teaching
you הלכה halacha that the institution... the marriage doesn't exist? You might
think there's marriage, it's telling you הלכה halacha in הלכות ייעוד. hilchot
yiyud. You might think that a minor could be מקדש mekadesh. a
girl, you might think that it could be ייעוד yi'ud with a
minor, קא משמע לן kamashmalan there's no marriage at all. Or is
it telling you there is marriage with a minor, but nevertheless there's
an exemption for the act of adultery because the kids are only...
because it's maybe not some degree of full marriage, okay?
Between two minors, a minor that's under nine years old and a
minor that's between nine...
No, we're even if we're talking between nine and thirteen, that's well,
that's the question. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara is assuming, which I
think is the reasonable assumption, that if you needed
the
פסוק pasuk to say there's no liability for adultery, it shows that
the institution of marriage does exist in that case. So where do
you get the institution of marriage for a minor if not through
ייעוד? yi'ud. And that would prove that ייעוד ye'ud does create קידושין
Kiddushin, even for a minor. Okay, so ah, you're so good, Michael.
אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, no, there's another case where we
could talk about marriage for a minor where the guy is not
sort of... where it happens a little bit more automatically. הכא ביבם
בן תשע שנים ויום אחד דאביבמת עסקינן. Hacha beyavam ben tesha shanim
veyom echad de'avivmat askinan. We're talking about a case of ייבום, yibum,
okay? Brother died, the surviving brother is over nine years old, his
ייבום yibum happens without any intent. Remember, right? If you know, the
גמרא Gemara. even has the absurd case of the guy falling off
the roof, okay? Without any intent, the physical reality of the act
of ביאה
creates ייבום. yibum. If that's true, so maybe even as long as
it's a physically considered an act of sex, the kids over nine,
even if you don't consider him a בר דעת, bar da'at, you
say there's no intent, ייבום yibum doesn't need intent even when it's
done by an adult. So the very physical reality of sex creates
them as his wife. And that would be a scenario where you
could have a marriage to a minor and the פסוק pasuk is
addressing that and it's not addressing the ייעוד ye'ud case. Okay, אהא
ביבמת עסקינן, avya yivmat askinan, דמדאורייתא חזי ליה, demid'oraita chazi lei, biblically
she's fit to him, meaning that there's a זיקה, zika, okay? And
מהו דתימא, ma'ut deiteima, כיוון דמדאורייתא חזי ליה, keivan demid'oraita chazi lei,
there's a זיקה, zika, there's an act of sex, okay? וביאתו ביאה,
Uve'iato biah, הבא עליה מתחייב באשת איש, haba'alah mitchayev be'eshet ish, maybe
you'd be חייב chayev for adultery, קא משמע לן kamashmalan that you're
not. So it's... the גמרא Gemara says yes, it's true, it seems
like we're talking about a case of marriage to a minor, but
that doesn't have to be ייעוד. ye'ud The other case where it's
possible is ייבום, yibum, which does not require any דעת, da'at, just
requires the act of sex. And that may be what we're talking
about. Now there's a fascinating... I'm going to answer what you're about
to ask. There's a fascinating debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot
here. which is what is the קמ"ל? Kamashmalan? רש"י Rashi says the
קמ"ל Kamashmalan is that even though there really, if that were to
happen, a nine-year-old boy, a ten-year-old boy would have sex with his...
with his sister-in-law after the guy... after the brother died, that they
would be considered husband and wife, and that קידושין kiddushin. would be...
יבום Yibum would be חל, chal, right, not קידושין, kiddushin the יבום
Yibum would be חל, chal, they'd be married. Nevertheless, there's an exemption
from the act... from the הלכה, halacha, from the punishment of adultery
if another man sleeps with her. But somehow, even though there's... they
are married, it's not a full marriage. Again, you know, it'd be
nice if you could say this in a parallel way, you know,
like if the... if either the man or the woman, you know,
you'd like to be able to say weren't adults, then even if
like on paper it's marriage, since they're not responsible yet, they can't
really commit to a married life together, live a... you know, what
a married life together really means, then to some degree it's not
yet a full marriage. It hasn't manifested as a full marriage. Okay,
but if we don't say that by a girl, at least we'll
say that by the boy. As long as the boy, again, in
this patriarchal society where the man basically defines it, if even he
is not yet... if he's not an adult yet, then even if
it's legally a marriage, it's not yet a full reality of a
marriage. And for whatever... and therefore, there is still going to be
an exemption from the laws of adultery, at least not punishable by
death. That's the way רש"י Rashi says it. תוספות Tosafot says no.
The קמ"ל Kamashmalan is, I might have thought that there was a
marriage, because there's a ביאה and there's... and there's... and it's יבום
Yibum and all of that. קמ"ל, Kamashmalan, this פסוק telling me that
there's no liability for adultery is telling me that it's not a
marriage. Okay, that's the קמ"ל. Kamashmalan. Okay, I know what's your question.
What?
What else according to תוספות, Tosafot, what other ramifications?
Uh, can I marry her sister after I grow up? You know,
I mean all these other possible things. Does she need a גט
get if now she wants to marry someone else, or would she
now need a גט get or would she need a חליצה? chalitzah?
Right? So there's... there would be all of those נפקא מינות. nafkaminas.
Okay, so if you look at רש"י, Rashi, very fascinating debate. רש"י
Rashi says... דמדאורייתא חזיא ליה, de-mi-de-oraisa chazei lei, about six lines from
the top, from the beginning of the narrow line... כלומר דזקוקה לו
באותה ביאה לכל דבר וקנאה ליורשה, kelomar dizkuka lo be-osa bi-ah le-khol
davar u-kna-ah le-yersha, he inherits her, שנתנו בן תשע שבא על יבמתו
וקנאה. she-natnu ben tisha she-ba al yevamto u-kna-ah. So רש"י Rashi says,
yes, she's really the wife, it's just that there's no חיוב chiyuv
of adultery. If you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, דמדאורייתא
חזיא ליה, de-mi-de-oraisa chazei lei, פירוש ככל דזקוקה לו בביאה יפה לכל
דבר קנאה ליורשה לטמא לה, pirush ke-khol d-izkuka lo bi-bi-ah yafeh le-khol
davar kna-ah le-yersha le-tamei lah, שנתנו בן תשע שבא על יבמתו וקנאה,
she-natnu ben tisha she-ba al yevamto u-kna-ah, וקשיא דאין לו אלא מדרבנן
ולפוטרה מן אחרים. ve-kashya d-ein lo ela mi-derabbanan u-le-patora min acherin. That
idea that it works if he's nine years old is מדרבנן, mi-derabbanan,
it's not biblical. So if you look at the end of תוספות,
Tosafot, right about five lines before the end where it says כלומר
אי לאו, kelomar ei lav, line starts with אי לאו. ei lav.
אי לאו האי קרא דמיעטה, ei lav hai kra de-mi-utah, if it
wasn't the פסוק that excluded her from adultery, הוה אמינא מדאורייתא חשובה
כאישתו, hava amina mi-de-oraisa chashuva k-ishto, קמ"ל דאינו קונה אלא מדרבנן. Kamashmalan
d-eino koneh ela mi-derabbanan.
Okay?
So this is the question. A nine-year-old boy, ten-year-old boy has sex
with his... his sister-in-law, the יבמתה, yevamtah, according to רש"י, Rashi, that's
marriage, there's just no חיוב chiyuv of adultery. And according to תוספות,
Tosafot, it's not marriage. All right? Anyway, back to the גמרא. Gemara
We still don't know if there could be ייעוד yi'ud for a
minor. All right? So the גמרא Gemara says, is it to protect
them or is it...
is that all to protect them, these regulations that it's not real,
or that it is real, if the adultery, say, from a minor?
What do you mean, to protect who?
Well, in other words, if the they were minors and and there
was a relationship outside of that relationship, then they wouldn't be punished.
Right. So is that a protection for them basically?
I'm not understanding who's being protected. These minors. How are they protected?
If this minor is married to this woman and now you're saying
that this woman sleeps with another man hasn't committed adultery, I don't
understand how the minor's interest is being protected.
Well, they're not being killed.
No, no, no, that's the other case. When the minor commits adultery,
he's not being killed. That's protecting the minor, but obviously, that's he's
under age. This case is saying, this minor boy is married to
this woman because through יבום, Yibum, the woman commits adultery and she's
not being killed. I don't understand how that protects the minor.
Okay. Oh, the woman...
oh, the woman is over... she's...
she's not a minor. Exactly. Okay. תא שמע, come and hear. אמר
רבי איבו אמר רבי ינאי אין ייעוד אלא בגדול אין ייעוד אלא
מדעת. Amar Rabbi Aivo amar Rabbi Yannai ein yi-ud ela begadol ein
yi-ud ela mi-da-as. So we have a statement.
Okay? It was a good question, we haven't really said how we
know this, but רבי איבו Rabbi Aivo just makes the statement: ייעוד
yi'ud. has to be an adult, presumably we obviously mean the son,
it's taken for granted that the father's the adult. Okay? It's only
if he's an adult and it's only מדעת. mi-da-as. תרתי? Tarti? Why
do you have to say both things? So the גמרא Gemara says,
מה טעם קאמר. ma ta-am ka-amar. What's the reason? מה טעם אין
ייעוד אלא בגדול? ma ta-am ein yi-ud ela begadol? Why is it
that there's... that the son has to be an adult? לפי שאין
ייעוד אלא מדעת. lefi she-ein yi-ud ela mi-da-as. Because the son presumably,
now you have to say he has to be made aware of
it, but it also raises the interesting question, like, do you see
the father doing it? Can the father tell his son, "Hey son,
I'm making her your wife"? And as long as the son's an
adult and he informed the son, it works? Or do you see
the father as being somehow appointed by the son, like representing the
son? So רמב"ם פוסק... Rambam paskens... means if I remember correctly that
the son has to give his father רשות *reshus* to be מיעד
*m'yaded* the girl. Okay, so how do you read מדעת *midaas*? You
could read, I think that this works better, that if it means
that the son is fundamentally the one who is marrying her, not
just he's been informed, but he's you know it's his דעת da'at
*daas* that is doing it, that obviously he needs to be an
adult. And the father just can represent, you know just is empowered
to do it, the son can permit his father to do it
and the father does it for the son. Okay, so if that's
the idea that the son is really the one doing it through
the father, obviously the son has to be an adult.
So that's like the שיטה *shita* of most ראשונים *Rishonim* that the
father is really not being מקדש mekadesh *m'kadesh* because it's the son
essentially who is.
I don't know what happened with most ראשונים *Rishonim*.
No, in other words let's say
whatever money is being used, the money that changed hands three years
ago or the remainder of the עבדות avdus? *avdus* now, the question
is still the... right, right, right. Okay, alright, so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says okay but anyway but there is an interesting question of
whether מדעת *midaas* means you got to inform the son or whether
מדעת *midaas* means the son is the one doing the ייעוד yi'ud.
*yiyud* through the father and then certainly that means that the father
that the son has to be an adult.
Does the girl have anything to say, it's like in other words...
we're going to get to that, we're going to get to that.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay, now ואיבעית אימא מאי
Mai מדעת *v'iba'is eima mai midaas* and and what how however there
is another way of reading מדעת *midaas*. One is the son has
to be an adult. Then there's the second הלכה halacha *halacha*. Okay
and it has to be מדעת *midaas*. Whose דעת da'at *daas*? Not
the son's, I mean maybe also the son's דעת da'at, *daas*, but
that's not the point. There's another דעת da'as, *daas* that's needed here.
מאי מדעת מדעת דידה *mai midaas midaas didah*. She it has to
be her דעת da'as *daas*. Now the important question is what does
דעת da'as, *daas* mean? Does she have to be informed or does
she have to agree and acquiesce? Okay, so let's take a look,
let's read the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*. Okay, so מדעת דידה *midaas didah*.
דתני אביי בריה דרב אבוה אשר לא יעדה מלמד שצריך ליעדה *d'tani
Abaye brei d'Rav Avuho asher lo yeada melamed shetzarich l'yada*. You have
to be מיעד *m'yaded* her. Now obviously what did he just say?
Obviously you have to be מיעד *m'yaded* her. So the way that's
read is more like להודיע *l'hodia* okay, to make her let her
know about it. רש"י *Rashi* says it's from לשון דעת da'as *lashon
daas* okay right, where's the רש"י *Rashi*? רש"י *Rashi* says לשון דעה
*lashon deiah*. Okay, so you have to make
her know. Who תני לה *tani lah*? So Abaye the son of
Rav Avuho taught this ברייתא Braita. *braisa* and הוא אמר לה *hu
amar lah* and he explains what it means. בקידושי ייעוד yi'ud ואליבא
דרבי יוסי Yosi ברבי יהודה דאמר מעות ראשונות ma'ot rishonot. לאו לקידושין
ניתנה *b'kiddushei yiyud v'aliba d'Rabbi Yosi b'Rebbi Yehuda d'amar maos rishonos lav
l'kiddushin nitna*. We're talking about קידושי ייעוד kiddushei yi'ud. *kiddushei yiyud*. Now
it's according to Rabbi Yosi bar Rabbi Yehuda who said מעות ראשונות
ma'ot rishonot. לאו לקידושין ניתנה *maos rishonos lav l'kiddushin nitna*. Now what
does this have to do... you see that's what Dovid mentioned before.
What does it have to do with what money is being used?
Because here's what we're saying is look if it was when the
money originally changed hands so when a father marries off his daughter
does she ever have to be... I mean yeah it was very
nice they asked Rivkah's opinion but הלכתית *halachically* does she ever even
have to be informed? She could be a one month old and
the father can marry off his daughter. So if it was when
the money originally changed hands, it was the father doing it and
there would be no requirement to make her to let her know
about it. But if it's happening after the sale and the father's
out of the picture and it's not the money that originally changed
hands, the קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* is happening through the remainder of the
service
that's you know owed, that it's between him and her. If it's
between him and her and not the father, so then he has
to make her part of the process. Now again the question is
she's still a minor. Okay, how much of the process can she
be a part of? But to some degree she has to be
part of the process and that means he has to at least
inform her. Whether it means she has to agree or not is
less clear, but at least he has to inform her she's part
of the process and that would explain if we assume that the
קידושין kiddushin *kiddushin* is happening later, the ייעוד yi'ud. *yiyud* is happening
with the not based on the money given to the father, then
we could understand that she has to be informed. Okay, so that's
one explanation of it. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak amar, אפילו תימא לקידושין ניתנו afilu teima l'kiddushin nitnu. *Rav Nachman
bar Yitzchak amar afilu teima l'kiddushin nitnu*. Even if it was the
original money that's now being used as קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* and it
was basically with the father, שאני הכא דאמר רחמנא יעדה *shani hacha
d'amar Rachmana yeada*. No, it's a special requirement. You know what? Technically
speaking you're right. It was the money given to the father that
becomes כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin. *kesef kiddushin*. Nevertheless, if you had just
been מקדש mekadesh *m'kadesh* the girl, so the girl would not have
to be informed, would not have to know nothing, okay? But the
תורה *Torah* is telling you when this happens through this process of
being a שפחה *shifcha* and then doing ייעוד yi'ud *yiyud*, even though
we're winding up using the money that we gave three years ago,
for this only works if she is informed and she becomes part
of the process in some way. Well no, when he's going to
do the ייעוד yi'ud, *yiyud*, he turns to the girl and says,
"Hey honey, I'm מיעד *m'yaded* you." Okay, so he can't just turn
to the father and say, "You know that money I gave you
three years ago, right? Now I'm deciding I've made up my mind,
I want to marry your daughter, we're going to do ייעוד *yiyud*."
Okay, he has to actually tell her. He can't just tell the
father. So even though if it was קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin* nobody would
have had to have told her, now that it's ייעוד *yiyud*, which
right, because it does not it's not clear at all that she
has to agree, that is correct. Okay, I'm pretty sure the... let's
take a look at the... but at least he has to inform
and at least he has to make her part of the process,
at least he has to make her part of the process, which
is a nice point. If she's becoming his wife, she should be
informed about it. Okay, but it's not required by קידושי קטנה, ktana
right? So anyway, let me just check the Rambam on this. Thank
you.
Are you thinking about a case where it's about the son who's
a קטן? katan?
No, no, no, we're off, we're no longer about the son. Yeah,
correct. We're back to the... just right. We've moved from one discussion
that the son has to be an adult and it has to
be from the דעת da'as of the son. And now we're saying,
forgetting the son, there's another הלכה halakha, here that whenever there's ייחוד
yichud with a girl, okay, right,
exactly.
That was sneaky, they didn't tell us.
I know. Okay.
Rambam says
like this: ואינו צריך ליתן לה כלום שממעות ראשונות לקידושין ניתנו, v'eino
tzarich litein lah klum shemima'ot rishonot l'kiddushin nitnu, ואינו מייעדה... v'eino mi'eyadah...
one sec, one minute.
וכיצד מייעדה... v'cheitzad mi'eyedah... no, no, hold on, hold on.
אין אדם מייעד אמה עברייה לו ולא לבנו אלא מדעתה, אף על
פי שכבר קיבל אביה מעותיה, שהרי הוא אומר ייעדה מדעתה.
ein adam mi'eyed ama ivriya lo v'lo livno ela mida'atah, af al
pi shekvar kibel aviha ma'oteiha, sheharei hu omer ye'adah mida'atah.
That's all the Rambam says. It has to be מדעתה. mida'atah. So
does מדעתה mida'atah mean מרצונה mirtzonah or does it mean by informing
her? You're right, it's still left pretty unclear about this.
Yeah, I mean, let's say she says, you know...
yeah, we... I... right. Nobody ever says she can object. So
presumably מדעתה mida'atah means informing her. If it meant מרצונה, mirtzonah, you
would expect somebody to say that if she objects, it's not חל.
chal. Because we have מיאון mi'un in other cases.
I know, but that's a rabbinic institution. It seems like דעתה da'atah
here means informing her, not acquiescence. Okay.
The son? He could say like, I don't know your son from
a hole in the wall, at least you have some dough.
Alright, right. Maybe אדרבה, adaraba, maybe she wants to object to him
because she knows what he's like. Okay, anyway, now the גמרא Gemara,
says like this. Okay, so we got the idea that the son
has to be an adult, it has to be the דעת da'as
of the son, which could mean the son actually has to want
it and permit his father to do it, which is the way
the Rambam פוסק'ן, paskens, and it has to be her דעת, da'as
which might just mean she has to be informed as opposed to
she has to agree or acquiesce. Alright, now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Finally we get to this issue about מעות ראשונות. ma'ot rishonot Okay.
מאי Rabbi Yosef b'Rebbi Yehuda? Who is this Rabbi Yosef b'Rebbi Yehuda
that we're always assuming is the one that says that it is
not the original
money? דתניא, D'tanya, ייעדה והפדה, אשר לא יעדה, ye'adah v'hepdah, asher lo
ye'adah, did not do ייעוד or redeem her. Okay, now, so the
combination, the juxtaposition of ייעדה ye'adah and redemption tells you the following.
Says Rabbi Yosef b'Rebbi Yehuda: צריך שישהא ביום כדי פדייה. tzarich sheyishei
bayom kedei fidyah. You can only do the ייעוד if there's enough
service left on her contract that she could redeem herself. So there's
at least a פרוטה's perutah worth of service left. If there's a
פרוטה's perutah worth of service left on her contract, she could redeem
herself with the פרוטה, perutah, buy her service back with the פרוטה,
perutah, and only then does ייעוד work. But if there's only ten
seconds left in the day, there's not a פרוטה's perutah worth of
service left after the end of six years, we're at the last
minute at the end of six years, and there's not one פרוטה's
perutah worth of service that can be done, then you can't do
ייעוד. So why not? Presumably it's because the ייעוד is being done
with the service that's owed and not with the מעות ראשונות. ma'os
rishonos So therefore there has to be enough... a פרוטה's perutah worth
of service left in order to enable the ייעוד. Okay, so מכאן
אמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אם יש שהות ביום כדי לעשות עמו
שוה פרוטה, mikan amar Rebbe Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda im yesh shehut bayom
kedei la'asot imo shaveh perutah, if there's enough time left in the
day at the end of six years to do a פרוטה's perutah
worth of service, מקודשת. mekudeshet. So the same way she could redeem
herself with a פרוטה, perutah, he could do ייעוד with that פרוטה.
perutah. And this is his... Rabbi Yose's reason... this פשיטא peshita establishes
the foundation for his claim that the מעות ראשונות is a father's
not מקדש. mekadesh Exactly.
ואם לאו אינה מקודשת. v'im lav einah mekudeshet. If not, not.
אלמא קסבר מעות ראשונות לאו לקידושין ניתנו. alma kasvar ma'ot rishonot lav
l'kiddushin nitnu. You see he's of the opinion that it's not the
original money, it's only the leftover money, and therefore there has to
be a פרוטה perutah of leftover service left.
So he's not דורש סמוכין doresh smuchin then, right?
He is. יעדה והפדה. ye'adah v'hepdah.
I mean, like in certain cases...
well, that's the next response. רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak אמר, now here's the debate: does Rabbi Yosef b'Rebbi Yehuda really
say it's not the original money? רב נחמן בר יצחק says no,
everybody agrees it's the original money. אפילו תימא לקידושין ניתנו. No, no,
no, he could even hold that it is the original money that
becomes כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. שאני הכא דאמר רחמנא והפדה, shani hacha
d'amar rachmana v'hepdah, it's
a גזירת הכתוב. g'zeirat hakatuv. Because of the juxtaposition of ייעדה ye'adah
and והפדה, v'hepdah, it says you can only do it when there's
a פרוטה's perutah worth of service left, but at the end of
the day you're not מקדש mekadesh her with the פרוטה's perutah worth
of service, you're being מקדש mekadesh her with the original כסף קידושין.
kesef kiddushin, Okay, so there's maybe one opinion, clearly the default of
the גמרא is to assume that it's the original money that becomes
the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin but it's possible that Rabbi Yosef b'Rebbi
Yehuda says that it's only the remainder money. It's possible he doesn't
mean that, it's possible it's גזירת הכתוב. g'zeirat hakatuv.
It's a nice premium on procrastination, doesn't it?
There you go. אמר רבא אמר רב נחמן אמר אדם לבתו קטנה
amar Rava amar Rav Nachman amar adam l'vito k'tana to see what
הלכות halachos we can infer from the... fact that the תורה allows
the creates this reality of ייעוד. And one of it gets to
this question which is if the daughter is, if the father's out
of the picture, if we say like רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rebbe
Yose beRebbe Yehuda that it's not the original money, this is the
question that a number of you were asking, if it's not the
original money and he's out of the picture and he's marrying her
off between him and her with the leftover service whereas she's only
a minor, how does that work? How can she accept the כסף
קידושין kesef kiddushin, with the leftover service whereas she's a minor? So
אמר רב עמרם אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Amram Amar Rav Nachman,
אמר אדם לבתו קטנה, Amar adam le'vito ketana, a man can say
to his underage daughter, צאי וקבלי קידושייך מדרבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. Tze'i
ve'kabeli kiddushayich mi'deRebbe Yose beRebbe Yehuda. We learn from רבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה Rebbe Yose beRebbe Yehuda that a man can say to his
daughter, go ahead and accept כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin, I'm okay with
it.
Okay, she thinks she was sold as an אמה.
No, no, I have my five-year-old daughter, I want to marry her
off to you, Michael, okay? And I say, you know, go over
to Michael's house, he'll give you some money and I'm okay with
it, that'll make you his wife. Okay, and that works. Now obviously
it's not שליחות shlichus because I can't be because I can't, you
know, she's a minor, she can't be a שליח. shaliach. But she
actually is the person who herself is מקודשת, mekudeshes, so I don't
exactly have to make her a שליח, shaliach, it could be her
יד yad because she's the person that's the one that's marrying. My
דעת, da'as my דעת da'as because I'm the adult and I'm providing
the דעת, da'as, combined with her receiving of it actually works. I
get the money, actually works to create a קידושין. kiddushin, Okay, now
תוספות Tosafos has a bit of a problem with this because תוספות
Tosafos says I don't
understand, how can she even be קונה koneh the ring? A minor
can't be קונה koneh anything, forget שליחות, shlichus, a minor doesn't have
קניין. kinyan. So תוספות Tosafos says well, a minor maybe it's דעת
אחרת מקנה אותו. da'as acheres makneh oso. If you're intending to transfer,
Michael, so we have two things happening. Michael is providing the דעת
da'as to be מקנה makneh her the ring, okay, so that allows
her when she, it's put in her hand, to be קונה koneh
the ring. She doesn't have any דעת at this. He provides the
דעת plus her hand lets her be קונה koneh the ring. I
provide the דעת that she should be married to Michael, plus she
did the receiving, and that makes her married. So it's our two
דעתות da'asos working through her hand that's receiving it. Okay, and that
works. And how does it work? Because in this case the father
isn't, he's the one getting back as it were the service, the
father isn't in the picture and she's מקודשת. mekudeshes. So that becomes
the model that something like that could work in another scenario. Let's
just read that. ולאו אמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מעות ראשונות לאו
לקידושין ניתנו, Velav Amar Rebbe Yose beRebbe Yehuda me'os rishonos lav le'kiddushin
nitnu, that it's not the original money, וכי משייר בה שוה פרוטה
הוי קידושי, vechi mishayer bah shaveh prutah havei kiddushei, and it's the
remaining פרוטה prutah of service that becomes the כסף קידושין, kesef kiddushin
and the father is not in the picture anymore, so הכא נמי
לא שנא, hacha nami lo shena, it also would have meant and
the only way it makes sense
is we must say implicitly from the fact that the father sold
her, it's like the father is saying if at any stage he
wants to marry you, that's what I want, I'm okay with it.
So it's the father's דעת plus her receiving of her service back
and those combined. So the same way if I sell my underage
daughter, I'm okay with you marrying this guy, I'm providing the דעת
and she goes and she receives the ring, the combination of those
two work.
Am I missing something about saying that in the משנה Mishnah it
says אשה נקנית בשלש דרכים כסף שטר וביאה? Isha niknes be'shalosh drachim,
Kesef, Shtar, u'Viah? There's now a fourth דרך derech here which is
עבדות?
Well yes, except we're putting it into a קידושי כסף. kiddushei kesef.
We're saying it's a type of קידושי כסף, kiddushei kesef, either the
מעות ראשונות or the remainder.
No, because it's still saying the remainder of the service becomes the
שוה פרוטה. shaveh prutah. And the very fact that we're now using
this as a model to prove something about normal קידושין kiddushin shows
that we are refusing to look at this as an exception, we're
trying to fit this into the normal rules. Right, there is that
tension though.
Right, but we are forcing it into normal rules and
therefore we're creating either the original כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin or a
later כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin. and then we're using it to teach
me something about a normal type of a קידושין kiddushin. that I
can tell my daughter. Okay, so but everybody gets the point? I
can have my daughter do it, I provide the דעת, she does
the act and we learn that out that that's the only way
to explain what's happening.
You're saying a person could be מקדש mekadesh her to somebody and
not say צאי וקבלי, Tze'i ve'kabeli, you just do it yourself.
Of course I can do it myself, I'm the father. The חידוש
chidush is that she can do the act as long as I
provided the דעת and we learn that out from this קידושי ייעוד.
Kiddushei Yi'ud. Okay, Michael, my apologies to your wife about getting you
married off to my underage daughter which I don't have. Okay, so
now the גמרא says like this, ואמר רבא אמר רב נחמן, Ve'amar
Rava Amar Rav Nachman,
so this רבא אמר רב נחמן Rava Amar Rav Nachman is again
really like working with this, fitting this into normal קידושין kiddushin. and
then making inferences.
המקדש במלוה ויש לו משכון מקודשת. Ha'mekadesh be'milveh ve'yesh lo mashkon mekudeshes.
So I'm going to read this way תוספות Tosafos reads this. Mike,
oh, let’s say a woman, okay, go, I lent this woman $100.
She gave me some type of a collateral about it, I don’t
know, her iPhone, okay, I’ve got her iPhone, I’m holding onto it
as collateral. And then I tell her הרי את מקודשת לי, harei
at mekudeshet li, I’m מוחל mochel the $100, and הרי את מקודשת
לי, harei at mekudeshet li, and that works, okay, because she gets
הנאה hana’ah because I was מוחל mochel the $100. Now, what does
that have to do with the iPhone as collateral?
So, so רש״י Rashi says I’m מקדש mekadesh her with the iPhone
or whatever, anyway תוספות Tosafos no, it says you’re being מקדש mekadesh
her with the מלווה, malveh, with the מלווה, milveh, with the loan.
So תוספות Tosafos only says no, ‘cause I might have thought that
as long as I’m still holding onto the collateral, maybe there’s not
enough גמירות דעת, gemirus da'as, like what does it mean that you
were מוחל mochel the loan? You haven’t given me back my phone
yet. Okay, and nevertheless, even though you’re still holding onto the collateral,
if you’re מוחל mochel the loan, that you can be מקדש mekadesh
with the הנאה hana’ah that the person gets with the waiving of
the debt. Now, where do you know this from? מידי רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה, mi'de'Rabbi Yosi be'Rabbi Yehuda, again from our case. לאו אמר
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה מעות ראשונות לאו לקידושין ניתנו, lav amar Rabbi
Yosi be'Rabbi Yehuda ma'os rishonos lav l'kiddushin nitnu, the original money wasn't,
is not the כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin So therefore, how do we
conceptualize this? This girl now, underage girl, she now owes me $100
left of service, right? She’s been working for me for five and
a half years, she still owes me $100 left of service. So
that’s like a loan, that’s money that’s owed to me. She’s going
to pay it off with service, but that’s money that’s owed to
me. Okay. היי הלוואה היא, hi halvah hi, it’s effectively a loan,
it’s not a purchase, it’s a loan. תוספות Tosafos says this also
gets to the question whether עבד עברי גופו קנוי, eved ivri gufo
kanui, ‘cause we’re looking at it as a loan and not as
a service. But she owes me $100 worth of service. והיא גופא
משכון היא. v'hi gufa mashkon hi. Now what’s my collateral that I’m
going to get my loan paid off? I have her in my
control. Okay. So therefore that’s my collateral, she’s, so she owes me
the money and I have her herself as collateral and she’s going
to now do the service to pay that off. And now what
do I do? I say to her, I’m waiving the remainder of
the 100, the $100 you owe me, I am giving it back
to you as it were for כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin, and that
works. And so that’s how I’m being מקדש her with במלווה, b'milveh,
I’m giving her back the money that’s owed to me, okay, and
I’m holding onto the משכון, mashkon, I’m holding onto her. Okay. And
therefore וכי משייר בה שווה פרוטה מיד הוי קידושין הכא נמי לא
שנא. v'chi meshayar bah shaveh prutah miyad havei kiddushin hacha nami lo
shena. So therefore and here too it doesn’t work. Now of course
it’s a, not a good comparison because in one case I’m מקדש
the woman and I still have her iPhone in my pocket. In
the other case, if she is herself is the collateral, then when
I’m מקדש her, I am giving her back the משכון. mashkon. I’m
no longer holding onto her as a שפחה as a type of
a collateral. Okay, so it’s a little, it’s a very complicated case.
But nevertheless, we’re going to move on.
Up until this second I thought we were now talking about a
regular case of קידושין, kiddushin but now we’re talking about a קטנה
ktana again, it’s the שפחה, it’s a... והוי שווה פרוטה מיהא הוי...
v'havei shaveh prutah miha havei...
No, no, we’re learning from the case of a קטנה ktana to
apply to a normal case of קידושין, kiddushin right, and we have
רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi and a משכון.
mashkon. Exactly. But it’s still a very weak comparison, extrapolating. Exactly.
That’s the whole point, like we just did before by the קטנה
being מקבל כסף קידושין. mekabel kesef kiddushin. If we are trying to
make this not an exception and fit it into קידושין, kiddushin then
we’ll be able to infer other הלכות halachos of קידושין kiddushin from
it.
But so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi was a fringe opinion. Now we’re
saying oh from יוסי you can learn this. We’re saying just according
to him or now we’re saying that we actually have a...
That’s a good question. Meaning, meaning, you know, are the חכמים chachamim
disagreeing about how ייעוד works, but in principle they would agree with
all the other assumptions that get dragged along with his position? Or
maybe the חכמים chachamim would disagree with all those assumptions as well?
I don’t know, you’re right, it’s a good point. It sounds like
רבה בר בר חנה... Rabbah bar bar Chana... oh, let's say רבה
או רב נחמן Rabbah o Rav Nachman is saying like, no, their
whole debate is how ייעוד works, but all these other assumptions maybe
are agreed upon. Alright, let’s try to get a little bit further.
תנו רבנן: tanu rabanan: כיצד מצוות ייעוד? keitzad mitzvas ye'ud? How does
ייעוד work? אומר לה בפני שניים. omer lah bifnei shnayim. Now notice,
again going back to your point though, that we are making this
fit into the norms of קידושין. kiddushin We had to identify what
is כסף קידושין, kessef kiddushin, so the next question to ask is
where are the עדים, eidim, where's עידי קידושין? eidei kiddushin? You need
עדים. eidim. Where’s this statement of הרי את מקודשת לי? harei at
mekudeshet li? So we’re going to put all that into the place.
אומר לה בפני שניים הרי את מקודשת לי, הרי את מאורסת לי.
omer lah bifnei shnayim harei at mekudeshet li, harei at me'oreses li.
Okay, we make this into standard קידושין. kiddushin. אפילו בסוף שש, afillu
b'sof shesh, even at the end of six, אפילו סמוך לשקיעת החמה,
afillu samuch l'shkias hachama, one minute before sunset. ונוהג בה מנהג אישות
ואינו נוהג בה מנהג שפחה, v'noheg bah minhag ishous v'eino noheg bah
minhag shifcha, and from that point on she’s your wife, she’s not
your
slave.
He has to do with הרי את
מיועדת לי
harei
at meyuedes li too, right?
Right, that’d be a good thing to say in this case. רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yosi be'Rabbi Yehuda omer, again the רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yosi be'Rabbi Yehuda, אם יש שהות ביום כדי
לעשות עמו שווה פרוטה מקודשת ואם לאו אינה מקודשת. im yesh shehus
bayom k'dei la'asos imo shaveh prutah mekudeshes v'im lav einah mekudeshes. No,
no, no, there has to be a פרוטה prutah worth of service
left.
משל, mashal, this could be a, you could like an analogy to
this, as a case that will teach you about this is like...
I’m going to again read this like תוספות, Tosafos, like another
תוספות. Tosafos. לאומר לאשה התקדשי
לי מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום, l'omer l'ishah hitkadshi li me'achshav v'le'achar shloshim
yom, marry me from now, starting now, and
and the it’ll end taking effect in thirty days. ובא אחר וקידשה
בתוך שלושים יום. u'va acher v'kidshah b'soch shloshim yom. So then the
obvious question is at what stage is she fully married? And if
somebody married her in the interim, will that interfere with this? So
we say, so we're starting with the assumption that in that case
here's the הלכה, halakha מקודשת לראשון. Mekudeshet l'rishon. Okay,
so if it's מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום, me'achshav l'achar shloshim yom, the
הלכה is that since it was מעכשיו, me'achshav, it enough began now
that if another guy tries to marry her afterwards, that would not
override. She's enough married to this guy now. Now, so okay, that's
all very lovely. What's that telling us? So that's gonna tell us
something about קידושי ייעוד. So let's just read one more line in
the גמרא. משל למאן? Mashal leman? What case of the קידושין kiddushin
or to whom is this משל mashal informative?
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehudah is not saying משל.
mashal.
That's just the גמרא, no, the ברייתא. אילימא משל לרבי יוסי ברבי
יהודה, Ilema mashal l'Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehudah, if it's telling me from
this case it can teach me something about רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה's
Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehuda case, האי אם יש שהות ביום כדי לעשות
עמו שוה פרוטה מקודשת ואם לאו לאו. Hai im yesh shah bayom
k'dei la'asot imoh shaveh perutah mekudeshet im lav lo. Wait minute, רבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yosei b'Rabbi Yehuda says the whole קידושין only
begins at the moment of ייעוד with the remainder of the service.
There's no comparison to מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום. me'achshav v'le'achar shloshim yom.
It didn't begin and finish, it all took place at that moment
of ייעוד. So אמר רב אחא בריה דרבא, Amar Rav Acha brei
d'Rava, no, משל לרבנן. mashal l'rabbanan. No, no, no, it's teaching me
something about the רבנן. rabbanan. For the רבנן rabbanan it is like
a מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום. me'achshav v'le'achar shloshim yom. You give the
כסף of purchase, it becomes כסף קידושין, but the קידושין doesn't really
take effect until three years later, five years later at the moment
of ייעוד. Okay, so everybody see how that's analogous? Right, the money
changes hands five years ago, the קידושין finalizes, you know, at the
end of five years. It's like מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום. me'achshav v'le'achar
shloshim yom. And therefore what this משל mashal is telling me is
what would be in a ייעוד case? Listen to this, this is
a very interesting case. I buy this girl, okay, I have yet
to do ייעוד. Michael comes along during the three years.
I haven't made the statement.
I've made the statement. She's been working for me for three years.
I haven't made up my mind yet. Michael comes along and Michael
says to her הרי את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li or
he says to the father הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet
li. Can he do it? Does that take effect? Or if at
two years from now, before the six years is over I say,
you know what, I made up my mind, I am מייעד. Then
it turns out that the קידושין began five years ago and Michael's
thing did not take. So that's what the משל mashal is telling
me. The same way מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום me'achshav v'le'achar shloshim yom
if Michael tries to interfere it does not take effect, here too,
if Michael tries to do something before I did the ייעוד during
the service, and in the end I do the ייעוד, it does
not take effect. It becomes like a מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום me'achshav
v'le'achar shloshim yom according to the רבנן. rabbanan. So first the גמרא
says פשיטא, pshita, isn't that obvious? It's not obvious, no. מהו דתימא,
Mah d'teima, הלא לא אמר לה מעכשיו. Hala lo amar lah me'achshav.
In the first case I said מעכשיו, me'achshav, I'd made up my
mind that I wanted to marry her, it started now and it's
gonna finish in thirty days. In that case obviously Michael can't interfere.
It already began. But in this case, A, I didn't say the
word מעכשיו, me'achshav, so maybe the whole thing only takes effect five
years from now. I used the original money, but it takes effect
five years from now. Maybe it doesn't even begin now. And I
haven't even made up my mind yet that I wanted it to
be קידושין. So I might think that Michael can interfere in that
case. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that what we are saying
is that when I say five years from now I'm מייעד you,
that turns the whole case into מעכשיו ולאחר זמן, me'achshav u'l'achar zman,
that the קידושין began when the money changed hands and it finishes
later, and if somebody tries to interrupt it does not ruin the,
it does not ruin,
it does not, you know, it does not interfere with it. Okay,
so we'll end with this.
Doesn't that mean like לרבנן יש ברירה בייעוד? l'Rabbanan yesh bereirah b'Yi'ud?
I mean.